Guide to the Prince Achille Murat Papers, 1809-1845 M0079
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Prince Achille Murat Papers
1809-1845
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Murat, Achille
M0079
3.5 Linear Feet
Scope and Content
Primarily letters from various members of the Murat and Bonaparte families to Murat. Includes correspondence regarding Murat's attempt to organize a Belgium Foreign Legion in the 1830's; manuscripts of his writings on politics, slavery, economics, and literature; and family legal papers. The letters are in French, English, and Italian. Napoleon is not represented.
Biography
Achille Murat, son of Caroline Bonaparte and Joachim Murat (King of Naples, 1808-1815), grew up in Paris and Naples as heir presumptive to his father's titles. After the fall of Napoleon he lived in exile with his mother, brother Lucien, and sisters Letizia and Louise at Frohscorf Castle in Austria. Upon reaching his majority he petitioned for a passport to America. In 1823, he arrived in New York where news of a Spanish liberal revolution reached him. He decided to violate his promise never to return to Europe and sailed for Gibraltar, but he arrived too late. Upon his return to New York, he took out American citizenship papers and married a great-grand-niece of Washington, Catherine Willis Gray. He lived in Florida and for a time in New Orleans engaged in farming and various highly speculative business ventures. In the revolutionary 1830s he returned to Europe to become head of the Foreign Legion of the new Kingdom of Belgium, hoping for a "call from Italy" which never came. Back in America he published a book on the United States which failed to catch the public fancy. Murat was a staunch supporter of slavery though he professed to fight for the liberation of man. He was engaged in continuous litigation with the French Government for the Murat properties seized in 1815. He also tried to compel his uncle Joseph (Napoleon's elder brother) to give an accounting of funds the Emperor had given him to us "as I would use it."
Provenance
Gift of Homer Spence, 1947-1951.
Access Restrictions
None.
Italy; France.; Bonaparte family; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Y; Murat family; Murat, Achille; Murat, Achille
- Series 1. Family Correspondence
  - Laetitia Ramolino Bonaparte (grandmother) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cardinal Fesch (brother of Laetitia and great uncle of Achille) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Joseph Bonaparte (uncle of Achille) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Joseph Bonapart to Marechal Clauzel? (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Julie (wife of Joseph) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Empress Marie Lousie (aunt of Achille) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lucien Bonaparte (uncle to Achille) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alexandrine (wife of Lucien) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Louis Bonaparte (brother of Napoleon) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hortense (daughter of Napoleon's first wife, Josephine Beauharnais) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Elisa (sister of Napoleon) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Felix Baciochi (husband of Elisa) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pauline Borghese (sister of Napoleon) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Camille (husband of Pauline) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jerome Bonaparte (brother of Napoleon) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Joachim Murat (father of Achille) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Caroline (wife of Joachim and mother of Achille), 1809 - 1810 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Caroline (wife of Joachim and mother of Achille), 1811 - ca. 1814 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Caroline (wife of Joachim and mother of Achille), circa 1815, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Caroline (wife of Joachim and mother of Achille), nos. 1 - 28, 1816 - 1824 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Caroline (wife of Joachim and mother of Achille), nos. 1 - 28, 1825 - 1829 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lucien (younger brother of Achille) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Christine Bonaparte (daughter of Lucien) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Zenaide & Mathilde (daughters of Joseph) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letitia and Marie (daughters of Lucien) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Catherine D. Murat (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Caroline. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Antoniette de Hohenzollern (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Copies of letters by Achille Murat. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letitia (sister of Achille) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Louise M. Rasponi (sister of Achille) (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Caroline Murat to Achille (oversize) (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series 2. General Correspondence
  - de Bandus (Achilles tutor) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Henry Bradfield. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Letters B. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters C. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters D. including D'Hautemesnil. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Philippi Girard. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letter G. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hopkinson. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters H & K (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters L. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lafayette/Levasseur (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General Felix MacDonald. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mercey. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Mosbourg. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters M. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters 0-S. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Thibaudeau (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters V-W. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Achille Murat to Lebel (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified letters [1 of 2] (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified letters [2 of 2] (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Series 3. Papers
  - Family papers (properties, wills, etc.). (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Murat papers on politics, economics, etc. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - On Slavery. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Official Documents (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Business. (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Murat Papers: Miscellaneous. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Murat Papers: politics, 1815 - 1822 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Murat Papers: Literature and studies. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Murat Papers: Works, 1824 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Murat Papers: American subjects. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Murat Papers: General topic. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Murat Letters about America, to Thibeaudeau. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Misc. manuscripts and printed items. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Volume of Letters, 1840 - 1845 (Box 6)